this video is sponsored by brilliant
board games have been a part of human
culture for thousands of years the
oldest record of a board game we know of
Senate dates back to 3,500 BC from
ancient Egypt and you can still play it
now in fact it's got a rating of 5.8 out
of 10 on Board Game Geek which is pretty
good for a game that's 5 a half thousand
years old although we're not sure these
are the original rules as there's no
actual written record of them we're just
kind of gu in what they might be we do
know that throughout history tabletop
games have served as entertainment
education and a way to bring people
together and nowadays there's a huge
range of different games and I've been a
fan of board games for most of my life
so I wanted to make a map of board game
see if I could capture this vast domain
and make sense of it also I've just
released my own board game called
stabber in the cabin which is available
now more details on that later in the
video weirdly the name board Gam a bit
of a misnomer as they don't always
contain boards if you go into a board
game shop there'll be loads of games
which just contain cards so generally
board games can include some combination
of a board cards dice playing pieces but
not necessarily any of them and a lot of
games also use a wide range of other
components like timers Spinners or a
load of other things the general theme
of this map is that all of the borders
are a bit fuzzy
but I've tried my best to structure them
somehow and we'll start our journey with
the abstract games which carry the name
abstract because they tend to be light
on story and theme and focus on defining
a set of rules that pit players against
each other as they try to outwit each
other to achieve a certain goal chess is
perhaps the most famous board game and
is an example of an elimination game
where you're trying to take your
opponent's pieces today chess is a pure
logical strategy game with no randomness
or hidden knowledge but interestingly
there are thousands of Chess variations
people have played throughout history
and some of the early versions used dice
for a random
element the game go is probably the most
famous territory control game where
you're trying to control as much of the
board as possible in position games you
don't capture your opponent's pieces you
just maneuver your pieces until the
opponent can't go anymore count and
capture or manala games are a family of
games where you move glass bead from one
pot to another to try and capture as
many as you can in alignment games like
NS and Crosses or Connect 4 players are
trying to connect a certain number of
their pieces or symbols together and
less well known a connection or
configuration games which involve trying
to connect pieces across a board or
configure pieces in certain Arrangements
in the abstract games I'm also putting
pencil and paper games like dots and
boxes which got me and my friends
through many tedious lectures
but paper and pencil games are very
versatile another example is the word
game hangman so these aren't restricted
just to abstract games similarly yachi
is an example of an abstract roll and
right game which involves rolling Dice
and checking the results of a list but
there are now lots of themed rooll and
right games where you use the results of
the dice SATA generate parts of a house
you're building or doing a Dungeon Crawl
which this takes them outside of the
abstract Realm in fact categorizing
games is really difficult and I think
the reason for this is because they
reflect human
creativity like in the other Maps I've
made um of different areas of science
there's a baked in structure that you
get from the nature of reality like
genetics for the map of plants but with
board games a big part of what's fun
about different games is their novelty
so what I found with this map is that
the structure are not the games
themselves elves but the common elements
of game design which crop up in many
different kinds of games so any specific
game is some combination of these
different game Design Elements and so
these design elements is what we're
going to focus on in this map a good
example of a design element comes from
Cross and Circle games where you try and
be the first to get your piece or pieces
around aboard and home again an example
is pisi a traditional Indian Game dating
from the 16th century which was then
modified in Victorian England into the
game
Ludo interestingly Snakes and Ladders
also comes from ancient India where it
was used to teach children about
morality The Snakes and Ladders being
vices and virtues on the way to
Salvation also did you know Monopoly
originally came from another game called
the landlords game which was designed to
show the evils of capitalism and Tarot
cards were originally used for gaming
not divination which then known for now
but I'm getting sidetracked the point I
want to make is today the concept of
moving pieces around a board has been
used by so many games it's kind of the
default picture of what a board game is
but fortunately this picture is wearing
out because since the mid90s people have
invented and modified loads of new
design elements which we'll look at in
the next section which I've called
optimization games a common theme
between many modern games is that they
make the players compete with each other
to solve some kind of optimization
problem where you're often trying to get
the most victory points or maximize some
other wi condition one example is worker
placement made famous by carcasson where
you have a limited number of worker
pieces which you can place to control
territory or do jobs but they're stuck
on the board and you can only get them
back when they've completed their goal
so you need to optimize where you place
your workers for the maximum points
similar to this is resource management
made famous by Settlers of Katan where
you gain resources over time and you can
spend these on building Your settlement
but also the places you build your
settlement then dictates what resources
you get and this is a feedback loop you
need to optimize for victory in tile
based games the skill is to place tiles
in an optimal configuration to fit them
together again carcasson is a great
example of this where strategic tile
placement is another core element to the
game
strategy Network and route building was
made famous by the game Ticket to Ride
where you try and develop connected
routes between
destinations turn order claiming is a
mechanic in games where there's an
advantage to going first typically in
games where you're competing for the
selection of moves or resources so
there's a strategy in these games to be
the first player in the next turn in
race games like the Quest for elderado
you're competing with other players to
get from one place to another as fast as
possible using some mechanics
and in engine builder games you're
trying to build combinations of actions
or resources that Cascade when you
activate them and you're trying to
optimize better combos than the other
players similar to engine builder games
at Deck Builder games or drafting games
like Dominion or seven wonders where you
try and build a powerful deck of cards
either by using basic cards to buy more
powerful cards or by taking turns to
pick a card before you pass them along
to the next player again again trying to
get as many victory points as possible
using some
mechanics now going further in that
direction you get to the realm of
trading or customizable card games like
magic or Pokémon but I'd say these are
distinct from board games because as
well as the game they have elements of
collecting cards and hunting for or
trading rare cards so I've put them
slightly outside the domain of board
games and finally there are push your
luck games like quacks of qul bird
where you have to balance the benefits
of forging ahead against the risk of
being penalized for pushing too far
which is kind of a gambling
mechanic in fact it's worth mentioning
gambling games because the history of
board games is intertwined with that of
gambling B gam is a really good example
of a game that was designed with
gambling in mind but is mostly now
played just as a board game and also I
have to mention poker because that's one
of my favorite games but if you've ever
been to a know you know that there's a
whole world of gambling games out there
which also fall outside of the scope of
this map now I want to look at another
important aspect of board game design
the interactions between players which
is a fun part of many games this can
come in the form of trading like in
Settlers of Katan where you can exchange
Resources with other players and are
free to haggle over the exchange rate
word for sheep then there are games
where players have to try and outbid
each other in auction games like power
grid or competing in share buying like
in the game
stockpile and negotiation like in
diplomacy where a lot of the strategy is
in making alliances with other players
and strategically breaking these
alliances at the right
moments then we have storytelling games
like Sherlock Holmes Consulting
detective which are weighted heavily on
the setting rather than strategic rules
and play almost like Choose Your Own
Adventure books now I can't mention
storytelling games without talking about
role playing games like Dungeons and
Dragons which I've also put outside the
realm of board games because although
role playing games share a lot of
similar feature to board games dice
rules and sometimes boards and
Miniatures the core of role playing
games are the imaginative storytelling
and improvisation which I think sets
them apart from traditional board games
in fact there are many other kinds of
tabletop games that although similar to
board games
would need their own entire Maps
Miniatures and War games are similar to
strategy board games but tend to have
much more involved rule sets than board
games and are often as much about
collecting and painting the Miniatures
and creating elaborate battle fields as
they are about playing the game although
you do get Miniatures in board games and
you also get war game style board games
too so again blurry boundaries but I
wouldn't consider say Warhammer to be a
board game but you also get war game
which instead of having Miniatures have
more abstract counters and are more like
simulation games in fact simulation
games are an entire land mass to
themselves and aren't always about war
you can make a game to simulate any
system but the focus of simulation games
is more on the accuracy of the
simulation rather than for
entertainment back to the board games we
also have many sneaky mechanics that
play around with hidden information for
example bluffing games like scar which
reward deceitfulness where success
depends on your ability to strategically
lie to your friends or hidden movement
games like Scotland Yard where one
player is the criminal secretly moving
around the board and the other players
are detectives who have to try and track
them down by guessing where they are and
there are many social deduction or
hidden role games like werewolf where
one or more players are secretly trying
to sabotage or kill the other players
now I'm a massive fan of these kinds of
games so much so I've made my own game
in this realm called stabbing in the
cabin which is a kind of cabin in the
wood style slasher film where I've taken
the mechanic of um a secret murderer but
I've put it on a board so there's also
some logical deduction involved as well
as the social deduction that you get
normally a big part of these games is
going on Vibes to try and work out who
the murderer is but because the secret
stabber can only stab people in
neighboring rooms you can use logical
deduction to figure out who the secret
stabber is and because each turn you're
all going to be in different rooms
there's a bit of strategy about which
room you choose to go in and also which
room you stab in to hide your tracks as
much as possible also this takes about
30 to 45 minutes to play so it's a bit
quicker and a bit more casual than other
social deduction games where the
deception element can get a bit intense
for some people so if you or someone in
your life is into board games or classic
B movie horror films give stabin a cabin
a look I've put links in the description
below and it's designed for 5 to 10
players but you can also play it with
three or four players with a slight
modification and yeah this is the first
game I've released um I did all of the
artwork I did a load of play testing on
it and I try to make it um color blind
friendly with these meeples and also
thought about accessibility as well so
I'm incredibly excited to share it with
you all if you want to get your hands on
the map of board games poster the Link's
in the description below and you can get
it with a bundle with the stabing in the
cabin as well coming back to the map
let's move on to games that are more
casual things you can pick up and play
with the family really quickly trivia
games like Trivial Pursuit have a long
history but also may have a bit of a
shorter shelf life than other games
because the questions have to be
Rewritten to keep up with the times word
games like code names or Boggle test
test the player's creativity with words
and language and memory games like
memory test people's memory and then
we've got dexterity games like Jenga
where the players need to use their
manual dexterity to balance blocks or
games where you need to build structures
out of odd-shaped blocks this group also
includes flicking games like croc andol
or
sauo so I think that's a decent overview
of the main elements of game design and
any particular game will be some
interesting combination of these
different elements although I have to
say there's many categories and game
mechanics that I didn't have time to
mention there's loads the website Board
Game Geek has it lists nearly 300
different ones so I had to pick a subset
here but let me know in the comments if
you think I've missed out anything
really important but I want to round off
the video by looking at a big part of
modern board games the setting or the
theme of the game this is the story line
and the motivation behind why you're
playing again there are way too many
settings to mention but popular genres
include Colony building trains business
Sports historical games crime nature or
environment anthropomorphic animals
fantasy science fiction mystery horror
zombies and many more the interplay
between the setting of the game and the
rules rules of the game I think is a
really interesting part of game design
and personally I think the best games
are those where the story and the
setting give a reason why the rules are
a certain way for example in my game
stabbing in the cabin the game only
works mechanically if there's one
teenager per room but the storyline
reason for this is It's a horror film so
everyone always has to split up that's
the first rule of horror films so I
think little elements like that give
rules some character and also make them
a bit more intuitive to learn so my
favorite games tend to be ones where the
rules and the setting mesh really well
also it's probably worth mentioning the
terms Euro game and Merit trash which is
how games are sometimes categorized but
I don't think this is a very good way of
characterizing games basically because
um historically it's been a bit
judgmental saying that Euro games are
good games and amerit trash games are
bad basically Euro games games which
focus on strategy and generally avoid
direct conflict between players things
like settlers of Katan or carcasson um
these are also known as German style
games I think because many of the
designers are German although that's not
exclusively true and ameritrash or
American style games are games which
focus more on theme storyline characters
and contain more random elements to them
things like heroquest or risk and
traditionally the term was used as a
derogatory term the trouble is none of
this holds up to much scrutiny because
nowadays all kinds of games are made all
over the world many games combine
elements of both sides and also a lot of
people love the Amera trash games that's
how I got into games because they're fun
to play and also a huge proportion of
them are not American risk is French um
heroquest in the Games Workshop style
board games come from Britain um and if
if you go back through games history the
modern ameritrash games actually Trace
their lineage back to military
simulation games which were invented in
Germany around 1800 making the amerit TR
games actually German style games anyway
fortunately the world of board games is
moving beyond these simple terms because
we've got a much better language now to
talk about games these days like the
stuff I've been using in this map and I
have to say love all kinds of games I
think there's really good versions of
all of the different kinds of game
design that I've mentioned in this map
anyway in the final part of this map I
want to talk about another very
important aspect of games the different
styles of game playay most Bard games
are two-player games or multiplayer
games but some especially the
storytelling games can also be played
single player also an interesting style
of game a Cooperative games like
pandemic where all of the players are
playing together against the game and
trying to beat the game
also most games are designed to be
symmetric in that all of the players
have the same options to begin with but
many games are specifically designed to
be asymmetric which I think is a much
harder thing to design but this
introduces an interesting Dynamic where
the rules and strategy for each player
or faction are quite different a good
example of this is root but many hidden
roll games are asymmetric too cuz the
murder is very different to the
Innocents and finally it's worth
mentioning camp or Legacy games which
instead of one-off games Legacy games
are designed to be played multiple times
over many weeks or months where the
result of one game has an impact on the
way that future games are played often
with destructible components or stickers
that change the game board this means
each group will play a unique Journey
Through The Campaign and I should
mention this kind of mechanic I think
came from role playing games which is
the default for role playing games but
has more recently been brought over into
traditional board games in a really cool
way and that's my map of board games My
Love Letter to all of the good times
I've had with friends around the gaming
table and to all the amazing designers
and artists who have spent their time
making fun experiences for us to explore
and personally it's been really
satisfying to contribute one small game
to someone's gaming shelf there's so
many demands on our time these days but
anytime I've got some free time to sit
down and play a game with friends I know
I'm in a happy place because I've
covered so many different topics on this
channel one comment I get fairly often
is how do you know so much
well most of that's research uh but also
I never gave up learning new things and
a really good way of learning something
new every day is using the app and
website brilliant because it's science
learning but built in a way that feels
more like playing a game like this kind
of intera activ ity where I can play
around with Concepts that I'm learning
about which really helps me get a feel
for them and develop an intuition for
the subject it's also got progress
tracking which really appeals to the
completionist part of my brain and this
is all backed up by top tier courses
developed by award-winning teachers and
researchers from the likes of IBM
Caltech Google and Microsoft amongst
others so if you're interested in
learning about science mathematics data
science programming AI from beginner
level up to advanced level check out
brilliant.org doos and through that link
you'll be able to get a 30-day free
trial and by clicking that link it also
helps support this channel which is
really appreciated and as an added bonus
if you decide to upgrade to the full
premium membership you'll be able to get
a 20% discount through that link thanks
so much for watching and thanks to
chance Encounters in Bristol for letting
me film with an excellent game
collection and I've got many more map
videos to come so I'll see you in the
next one